Hello guys, welcome back to the
channel.
So in this video, we will talk about
the oops concepts in Python part 2,
which are class variables.
If you haven't seen the previous
video, I will put that link in the
description below and also this
place.
So please go ahead and watch that
video and come back.
So in this video, we will learn
about class variables.
But before class variables,
I wanted to explain a common
situation where a lot of developers
will do the mistakes while doing the
classes.
And this mistake, you will not face
it when you are working alone.
This mistake you will face it when
you are working in a team and team
collaboration is the only mistake.
I will tell you how this mistake
will happen and I will also tell you
how to avoid this mistake.
So this is something that I am
sharing from my personal experience.
In the last video, we created this
class, which is basically an
employee class.
We have the init method and it takes
three variables, first,
last and pay.
And we know what is self and
everything.
And we derived an email from the
first dot lower and last dot lower.
And we have two different methods,
which is basically a full name and
the increase pay and increase pay
and in increse pay function
I made a small change where I put
the hard code value of one point
zero four last class low.
We put the value as percentage but I
removed that and I will tell you why
in some time.
So let's say there is an employee
class and you created an instance of
that class in the employee one by
passing the values.
Rahul one, Sharma one,
eight lakhs.
Now when you say print employee one
dot dict, it is going to give you
what are the details.
What is the first name, what is the
last name, what is the pay and what
is the email.
This class is created.
The next day, a person in your team
wants to update the salary of this
employee one instance.
So he wants to update it pay
equal to nine lakh rupees.
But he made a typo and put it as
PYA example.
So usually VS code is showing the
issue, but it will not throw issue
when you execute the code.
So let's say I will execute this
code.
The pay increase still has the eight
lakh rupees, but it is not throwing
any error.
But what if I print this employee
one dot dict after this one and
let's execute this and look at this
one.
Initially, we have the Rahul,
the last name is Sharma and pay
eight lakh rupees and email.
But it didn't update the
pay value because it didn't
recognize what is the spelling PYA.
And it added a new attribute to this
employee one instance with the new
typo that is created PYA.
So it should not have happend?
Now, Python inherently will not
throw any errors on this one because
Python thinks that we are all adults
and will not make any mistakes.
So when you create a new attribute
that is not present in the instance,
when you created this class,
then what Python will do is it will
create that attribute to this
particular instance as an additional
attribute.
That's why you can see that this is
coming at the last one here.
It's basically a typo,
but here the pay is still
eight lakh rupees, but not the
latest one.
OK, that is what it is happening.
So you think the pay has been
updated, but Python happily created
a new attribute and your code runs
properly and you'll not find any
issues.
And these are the kind of bugs that
are nightmare to debug for
developers.
And where else mistakes can happen
So maybe you created a list of
employees and a list low.
You have all the instance of all
these employees.
And then if I go to the first one,
which is basically the which is
basically the instance for the Rahul
Sharma.
And if I put something called as
department,
I am adding a new attribute again
and then I will put engineering.
What if I iterate through all of
these employees for employee in
employees
print employee department?
So when you execute this piece of
code,
so here what is happening initially
when you say this is this is my
employee one instance and this is my
employee two instance and you are
iterating through all of these
instances.
But merely employee one instance key
you create a new attribute
department,
but employee to key our department
and it led to because you didn't
have the department as an attribute
in your in it function.
So when you are iterating through
all of your employees and when you
are printing the department,
Its fine for first one
but second then key it will throw an
error because that attribute is not
present when you defined in the in
it.
So when you are working
in a team actually,
so how to fix this you learn to fix
there is something which is
basically called as slots.
So what are the slots?
So when you create this class at the
start,
underscore underscore slots
underscore underscore here equal to
you provide the list of attributes
that this class can accept.
Let's say first and then I will put
last and then I will put pay.
So what we are saying we are
enforcing the class such that
you can only have these attributes
but not any other attributes.
So let's try all of this right now
and let's do this.
The same code we are going to
execute again,
but after adding slots and matter
and if you execute this now,
look at the output say attribute
error employee object does not have
this attribute.
Initially when we don't have the
slots,
we didn't get any error and it
updates the dictionary of that
employee one instance.
But right now,
if you don't want to make those kind
of mistakes,
it's always recommended to use this
kind of slots,
which is enforcing the python to not
create more attributes which are not
necessary.
So this is enforcing python.
So when you are in a team or when
you work in a company,
this is very important.
This is what makes or breaks your
production code actually.
And then we will now talk about an
important concept which are called
class variables.
If you look at this in our code,
when we say increase pay,
here I did a hard code value of 1.04
By default, whenever I call this
function,
I am going to increase the salary by
4 percent.
But this is applicable for every
employee.
Because you are doing it for every
single time when you call this
function.
But what if the company decided to
not put only 4 percent,
but only 7 percent flat and wherever
you put 1.04,
I need this scale 1.07.
It is very cumbersome.
And then sometimes you want to give
specific arrays to specific
employees.
Maybe employee 1 gets 10 percent,
employee 2 gets 15 percent,
and remaining everyone gets 5
percent.
So doing this hard code is a very
bad option.
So that is where you will use
something called as class variable
and you define that class variable
just after the class definition.
You will not put that inside any
methods.
You will just put it something like
this.
Let's say I want to raise
percentage, raise percentage equal
to 1.04.
So this is a variable that we are
defining inside a class
and that is why we call it as a
class variable.
So what does this mean?
This class variable will be
applicable to all of these
instances.
If you create any employee instance,
you can access this pattern for
every employee instance.
So now you created this class
variable.
And now we have the hard code value
of 1.04.
We will change it with the class
variable which is basically raise
percentage.
And here VS Code is throwing a
warning because I don't know what
raise percentage is.
I need to put self.raisePercentage
because everything goes in the self.
I will talk about some differences
why it is self and why not a class.
We will talk about that so don't
worry.
So how do we put it?
Now let's create two instances
of these employees.
And then let's do this here and I
will create instance one
which is basically Rahul Sharma and
8 lakhs and then Priya Patel and 9
lakhs.
And then one of the thing is you can
access this class variable
using something by the class name
employee.raisePercentage.
So what we are doing?
We have this class which is our
employee class.
After that you are accessing this
class variable using the class name
dot the variable
and you will get 1.04.
After that here you are using self.
And what self means is whenever you
are creating an instance of a class
and employee one will be acting as
self.
And whenever you are creating a
second instance employee two will be
the self.
So that means if you want to access
the specific employee
.raisePercentage
you can do employee one
.raisePercentage and employee two
.raisePercentage.
So these three are saved by default
so I will get the output as 1.04.
Now let's execute the code and see
the output.
1.04, 1.04 and 1.04.
What can we do now?
I can apply this method by saying
increase pay.
So what I will do is I will say
employee one dot raisePercentage
and I will put this one and increase
pay not raisePercentage.
And then I can just print employee
one dot pay and if I execute this
it is going to create initially 8
lakhs and it is working perfectly
fine.
Now what we are going to do is we
will go one step deeper.
So we have class variable here.
After class variable we created the
instance of this employee
by using employee one and employee
two.
But before doing anything we are
just printing the attributes.
When you execute this first Rahul,
Sharma and pay and email came.
Priya, last and then pay came and
then email came.
But if you look at this here
raisePercentage is not there for
employee one but for employee two.
But when I access print employee
one, employee one dot
raisePercentage
let's execute this and getting 1.04
in the queue.
Why is it happening?
So when you create a class variable,
this class variable is going to get
applicable for every single thing.
So what if I will print something
which is employee dot
employee dot underscore underscore
dict.
So now let's look at all the
attributes that this class has.
Look, name, flash to pay and
raisePercentage.
Look, this dict has the
raisePercentage 1.04.
That means it is in the class.
So now when employee one dot dict
does not have this raisePercentage
how is this python finding this
employee one dot raisePercentage as
1.04?
Tell me.
So the issue is when you say the
first when you write employee one
dot raisePercentage
what python does is
in the first step it will try to
find out whether the employee
one dot underscore underscore dict
has this variable which is
raisePercentage.
Now if this raisePercentage is not
in employee one dot dict then it
will go to the second step
and it will look at whether this
raisePercentage
is under the class which is
basically employee dot underscore
underscore dict.
So if it is in this then you will
access that value directly.
If it is not in this then it will
throw an attribute error.
Now the second topic which is how to
override these class variables.
So by default the raisePercentage is
1.04 but what if I want to change
this value to maybe 1.07?
So I can directly change from the
class value itself.
I can say employee
dot raisePercentage equal to
1.07.
And if I print employee dot
raisePercentage this is going to
change it to 1.07.
But at the same time what if we will
do employee one dot raisePercentage
and then we will also print employee
two dot raisePercentage
and all of these will become 1.07 by
default.
Because we are changing at the root
level which is basically employee
dot raisePercentage is 1.07.
So can I change from the individual
level?
Yes, so now everything is set
to 1.07.
After this I will put employee one
dot raisePercentage and
I will put it as 1.15.
This means I am changing the
raisePercentage for a specific
employee instance but not every
single thing.
And then let me print all of this
here.
Now let's try to execute this.
Now look at it by default our class
has 1.07 and this is for 1.15 only
for a specific instance of employee
one that we did here.
Employee one dot raisePercentage
equal to 1.15.
And then the last class instance
which is employee two it is going to
stay same.
And after that you might get one
more doubt.
Sir we are accessing employee dot
raisePercentage.
So can I just say instead of self
can I do employee dot
raisePercentage?
Yes, you can absolutely do this but
you are always accessing this global
variable not the self instance
variable.
Self will always replace with the
instance that you created during the
class creation employee one and
employee two.
If you put self here you will access
and you will modify these individual
values.
Instead of self if you put employee
by default you are only accessing
this value which is default class
variable of this particular class.
So which one should I use?
I usually never use this because I
have the freedom to change the
individual classes and also the
freedom to change the global level
class variable as well.
So I prefer to keep it like this but
if you want you can keep it as an
employee dot raisePercentage as
well.
And maybe let's take one more
example which is let's say you are
creating employees every time and
you want to count how many employees
are present in your company.
So this number of employees concept
is applying on a company basis not
on an employee basis.
So I will create one more variable
which will say count equal to zero
and then whenever we are creating an
instance of this class by default
this is going to get executed.
So whenever I create an employee I
will increase my count count plus
equal to one.
So every time when I create this
employee instance it is going to
increase my count but I cannot
directly access count I will say
employee dot employee dot count.
And if I do this and if I print
after all of these things let's say
print employee dot
count employee dot count.
And if I execute this it will give
me an output of two.
So when I created the instance for
the first time so let's say so when
I call this for the first time it
goes here and the value is zero and
this will get initialized.
And it will create the email and
here you are updating the count as
plus one.
So initially when you created for
the employee one this value became
plus one and when you executed this
line the second line this value is
already plus one.
And when you execute this definition
again this plus one is going to add
one more plus one this will become
two and this count will become two
and that is what you are printing
here and this will give me the
output as two.
That is how the global variable
works and think about logically.
Now this employee count will be the
same for everyone.
It is not that I employee one count
separate employee two count
separate.
That is why it is always beneficial
to use that as a global class
variable rather than individual self
dot count.
Here I can technically do self dot
count.
But that doesn't make any sense.
Let me show you an example as well.
We will create one more attribute
which is like self dot count.
This is a very interesting use case
and let's see how it happens.
Whenever you are writing self self
is always this employee one and
employee two.
Because it is not from a class self
will always be replaced by the
instance that you are calling for.
So it could be employee one or
employee two.
But we have the global value which
is called as count as well.
Let's print employee dot count
employee dot count and then after
this I will also print employee one
dot count.
So what is happening here let's
execute this and the output into one
comma two.
So let's look at what is the output.
Here the output is one and here the
output is two.
Why it is one and two.
So this is a very interesting use
case guys.
So let's understand what is
happening.
So initially when you executed
employee Rahul Sharma and 8 lakhs
and here count value is zero.
And this will get executed and here
the initial value of count is zero
and you are adding plus one.
So this will become plus one.
After that you are looking self dot
count.
So self dot count what is happening
here.
So first python will look into
employee one dot underscore
underscore dip underscore
underscore.
Now if there is a count value in
this it will update that.
If there is no count value in this
then it will fall back to this count
which is the class count.
So we don't have this value so it is
already plus one.
You are making plus one and that
will become two and that is why
employee one dot count is becoming
two later on.
So it is a little bit confusing.
So it is better not to use this self
dot count if it is a global
operation that every employee or
every instance can have.
So these are all the common mistakes
that people usually do when creating
the class variables.
So our summary is whenever you have
a variable that is applicable to all
those are called class variables.
And you are going to define all of
these the moment you define your
class.
After that if there are any
variables or attributes that are
specific to a particular instance
these are called instance variables.
And each instance has its own copy
but these class variables cannot
have multiple copies.
So how to decide which one to use.
First you always ask a question
whether the variable we create is it
going to be different for every
instance or is it going to be same
for every instance.
If it is going to be same for every
instance use class variables if it
is not then use instance variables.
So now we will quickly jump back to
our resume builder code.
If you look at this class this class
is basically called as seniority
level.
Then we declared all of these which
are class variables shouldn't it
class initialization.
We have all of these values and then
we have something which are normal
instance variables as well.
But later on if you look at this one
which is pipeline step and even
these are all the class variables.
So now you are understanding what is
happening in this code step by step.
We still have something to
understand what is this thing and
the class inheritance and all of
those things.
And we will learn all of those
concepts in the next video.
So stay tuned for the next one which
is basically class inheritance.
And if you are enjoying the content
please subscribe and if you know
someone who wants to learn all of
these concepts in detail.
Please share it with them and if you
are learning something new.
Please also comment and if you have
any doubts at all and comment
change.
I will reply to each and every one
of the comment.